



PRADEEP REDDY visit my website

ws⊘certified



Frisco TX (Dallas TX) City



+1 610 405 7885 Phone Number



Pradeepreddy.Alla@gmail.com



https://www.linkedin.com/in/pradeepreddy-8a04792 URI

EDUCATION

MS Software Systems

Birla Institute of Technology & Science, Pilani

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Sciences Osmania University, Hyderabad India

EXPERTISE

Enterprise Architecture (Business, Data, Application & Technology Architecture)

AWS & Azure Cloud Solutions Architecture

Big Data (Iceberg, Spark, Trino, Starrocks, Hive & Hadoop)

Generative AI, Data Science Classification, Regression, Neural Nets, Clustering, NLP & Time Series with Scikitlearn, Pytorch and Tensorflow

BI/Analytics (Tableau, Alteryx, Cognos, Looker, Power BI)

Domain Driven Design/ Design Thinking /UI / UX

Java EE (MoM, SOA/Micro Services, JCA, EJB, Spring, Angular JS/Material), Scala, Python & R

Technology Leadership | AIML Product Management | Machine Learning | Generative AI | Enterprise Architecture | Big Data Architecture

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Strategic product leader with 20 years of experience delivering impactful products and services. Expertise spans product management (inbound, outbound, GTM), enterprise architecture, big data, and machine learning. Currently, drives product strategy for Jupyter Workspace, Generative AI/Foundation Model Batch Inference, and Spark at Apple.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Apple | Lead Product Manager, AIML Data Platform November 2022 – Current

- Transformed AI/ML developer experience across Jupyter and VS Code, enhanced by AI pair programming (Roo Code) extensions, dedicated agent development tools, and a Prompt Studio.
- Pioneered a scalable Gen AI / Foundation Model LLM Batch Inference Service using Kubernetes and Apache YuniKorn, managing several launch cycles since inception. The service boasts 9+ billion prompt completions for 750+ daily active users.
- Implemented Metering and cost attribution for the Batch Inference Service and established cross-departmental chargebacks. Partnered with Corporate Finance to deliver the chargeback solution within three months of launch, improving cost transparency and accountability.
- Transformed Apple's internal ML/AI ecosystem by launching and scaling the AIML Jupyter Workspace, providing a centralized platform for 2000+ monthly active users across 14+ organizations to collaborate and innovate.
- Chartered a Product Advisory Board with power users from 14 organizations to guide the evolution of Jupyter workspace.
- Collaborated with NVIDIA Spark team, Apple Spark Engineering & internal customer teams to enable unified AI and Data pipeliens using Torch Distributor on Spark with GPU's.
- Inspired by success of Batch Inference Service, Led the ideation and development of Serverless Spark using Apache YuniKorn and dynamic namespace assignment in Kubernetes to enhance resource management and isolation.

AWS | Sr Product Manager, SageMaker Autopilot and Automatic Model Tuner December 2020 - November 2022

- Identified total addressable market, established a new value hypothesis, gathered competitive intelligence, defined product strategy for SageMaker Autopilot and Automatic Model Tuner to achieve 91% CAGR.
- Working backwards from the goals, defined product vision and roadmap in collaboration with engineering, PMM & business development teams.
- Led data driven GTM by dogfooding AutoML to predict customer life time value (30 days / 90 days/1 Yrs/2 Yrs), return probabilities, churn prediction to achieve product / market fit.
- Defined and led UX workshops by creating customer journey and user empathy maps, with a goal to improve user retention using metrics such as Ratio of DAU to MAU, T-13 Retention Rate etc.,,
- Led SageMaker Autopilot partner strategy and execution for Domo, Redshift, and Snowflake.

Qubole | Principal Product Manager – Data Science

December 2018 – November 2020

- Led product strategy for data science capabilities, encompassing machine learning, Jupyter notebooks, experiment tracking, deep learning, and K8S Python runtimes..
- Worked closely with product, engineering & executive leadership team on the product vision & roadmap.
- Built market segmentation & capability maturity models for data science to help define product vision and strategy.
- Led RStudio OEM partnership with a goal to provide a managed RStudio Server Pro

SKILLS

UI/UX/DESIGN THINKING

ENTERPRISE ARCHITECTURE UI/UX/DESIGN THINKING







DATA SCIENCE

PRODUCT/PROGRAM UI/UX/DESIGN MANAGEMENT

THINKING







ACHIEVEMENTS

CERTIFICATIONS

I'm certified in Enterprise Architecture from TOGAF & SUN Microsystems (now Oracle)

RECOGNITION

I have won awards of appreciation from my employers and customers/stakeholders alike

TRAITS

ENTREPRENEURIAL LEADERSHIP

I love ideating & executing on Entrepreneurial

STRATEGIC & TACTICAL

I can balance both strategic goals and tactical needs.

LEARNER / SEEKER

I believe that when you stop learning, you stop

EXECUTION

Doing is more fulfilling to me than talking / thinking about it

INTERESTS



EMPLOYMENT HISTORY (CONTINUED)

Qubole | Technical Director / Big Data Solutions Architect May 2017- Feb 2020

- Led a team of 5 solutions architects to support East and central region field engineering focused on Pre-Sales.
- Provided Big Data architecture consultation services for ensuring customer success on key strategic accounts.
- Provided architectural blueprints for building Data Science solutions viz., Recommendation Engines using Spark ML ALS (Alternating Least Square), Regression, Classification, Text Analytics, Clustering & Time Series using SparkML & scikit-learn.
- Evangelized reference data lake architectures in the cloud for data engineering & data science.
- Designed blueprints for big data lake concerning meta data management (Business Glossary), data ingestion & refinement processes.
- Expert level understanding of Hadoop(YARN), Hive, Spark & Presto
- Helped customers build batch ETL pipelines using Hive/Spark, as well as Real Time Data Ingestion pipelines using Kafka & Spark Structured Streaming.
- Subject Matter expert on integrating data analytics tools like Tableau, Alteryx & PowerBI with Hive, Spark & Presto through ODBC/JDBC drivers.

Quest Diagnostics | Enterprise Solutions Architect, Big Data Architect February 2006 - May 2017

Enterprise Architecture, Big Data, Cloudera Distribution Including Hadoop(CDH), Hive, Spark, Spark ML, Data Science Notebooks, Stanford CoreNLP, Tableau, Alteryx, Netezza, Exadata, Python, R, Scala, Java EE, JCA, Spring, PowerBI, Tableau, Plotly, Matplotlib

- Key Member of Technology Advisory Board advising CIO & CTO office and owner of Technology Radar (Thought Works Tool for Technology Evangelism).
- Key member of Big Data Architecture Council Technology evangelist for Hadoop/big data related technologies with successful execution of several POC's to justify
- Led Design Thinking Workshops for UX design using techniques viz., A/B Testing, User Empathy Maps, Rapid Prototyping.
- Provided solution architecture for several BI solutions that required data from various data sources to be processed and refined into DataMart's using Apache Spark, Sqoop, Hive & Impala, Netezza & Exadata.
- Led several Advanced Analytics projects like Text Analytics, Sentiment Analysis & Topic Modeling on client support cases, customer complaints (Using Stanford CoreNLP & Apache Spark)
- Designed Blueprints for big data lake concerning Meta Data Management (Business Glossary), Data Ingestion & refinement processes.
- Led the Design and architecture of RESTful webservices using HL7v3 & Jersey framework for Realtime specimen tracking web services.
- Architected the interfaces for the ILOG 6 Business Rules Management System.
- Proposed and implemented the Java Connectivity Architecture 1.5 specification as an alternative to commercial integration engines that yielded \$150k annual savings when compared to COTS.

Computer Associates | Sr Software Engineer

October 2004 – February 2006

General Electric | Software Engineer

April 2002 – October 2004

Java EE, Spring, Hibernate, Struts, Java Server Faces, JSP, C++, SOAP/Restful Webservices

CERTIFICATIONS AND PUBLICATIONS

- TOGAF 9 certified, AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate
- Sun Certified Enterprise Architect for Java 2 Platform, Enterprise Edition.
- Quality Six Sigma Green Belt Certified Professional from General Electric.
- Machine Learning by Stanford University on Coursera. Certificate earned on February 21, 2016 - https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/SVM7P4SLR47X
- Blog Posts

https://www.linkedin.com/in/pradeep-reddy-8a04792/detail/recent-activity/posts/